# SETH CHART, PhD

Towson, MD, 21286 | 443-303-7114 | seth.chart@protonmail.com | GitHub: sethchart | LinkedIn: sethchart | sethchart | sethchart |

#### **Data Scientist**

Experience in data acquisition and data modeling, statistical analysis, machine learning, deep learning, and NLP. With a background in mathematics and database management, I bring strong skills in project management and education that help data driven companies realize their mission.

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

Python, OOP, SQL, scikit-learn, NumPy, Pandas, Keras, Pyspark.

#### TECHNICAL PROJECTS

## **Baltimore Real Estate Investment**

Time series models identify five zip codes in the city of Baltimore, MD with the highest expected two year ROI for single family homes.

- Collected relevant data from Zillow to ensure that the model was trained on up-to-date data.
- Designed a unique data structure to facilitate modeling each zip code separately to maximize model accuracy.
- Implemented OOP to provide seamless interaction with the model and encapsulate complexity.
- Produced a portable and scalable solution that can easily be applied to other and larger regions.

## **Pump it Up Data Mining the Water Table**

A competition submission identifying water wells in Tanzania that require repair.

- Built an end-to-end machine learning pipeline using scikit-learn to take raw data to reliable and replicable predictions.
- Executed a cross validated grid search of model hyper-parameters to ensure selection of an optimal model.
- Produced an XGBoosted random forest model that was ranked 385 out of 10,307 submissions (96th percentile).

## **Housing Market Analysis**

Used publicly available data to predict house price in King County Washington.

- Cleaned data and engineered features to ensure model quality and accuracy.
- Evaluated model hypotheses to ensure validity of results.
- Explored and visualized geospatial data to gain insight.

## **EMPLOYMENT HISTORY**

Database Manager, Immune Deficiency Foundation, Towson, MD

05/2019 - Present

- Coordinated integration between peer-to-peer fundraising platform and main database, essentially eliminating manual data entry and opening new revenue streams for my organization.
- Project managed the design, development, testing, and implementation of a custom volunteer management platform to eliminate manual data reconciliation and annual costs associated with the existing solution.
- Initiated effort to develop an organization wide process manual, which contributed to the decision to migrate to new database infrastructure that will better support organizational needs and goals.
- Leading database migration to provide better staff user experience, improved data model, and more automated workflows.

Lecturer, Towson University, Towson, MD

08/2016 - 05/2019

- Coordinated a multi-year pilot study implementing study sessions for undergraduate statistics students to evaluate efficacy in improving student outcomes. Presented findings at 2018 RUME Conference in San Diego.
- Selected as a 2018 Project NEXT Fellow a fellowship for innovative mathematics education.
- Launched and coordinated the Mathematics Testing Center to streamline makeup testing and vastly reduce administrative effort.

# **EDUCATION**

Flatiron School, New York, NY

08/2020 - 01/2021

Immersive Data Science Bootcamp program, January 2021

University of Victoria, Victoria, BC

08/2011 - 06/2016